To fast is to hunger for more of God.
We fast to offer our whole selves, including our whole body, to God.
To grow in holiness.
To amplify our prayers.
And to stand with the poor.
Fasting is one of the most essential and powerful of all the practices of Jesus.
It's an ancient discipline whose time has come.
Wow.
Thank you, Ryan and Canvas Church, for inviting me to come and join you all this morning.
I do want to also thank Ryan for giving me the hardest one of these four sermons on fasting.
Yeah, it's really sweet and kind.
You're such a gentle pastor.
For some of you who are looking up here and wondering who I am, most of you probably know me.
But for those of you who don't, my name is Nick Payne.
I serve here locally at Crossroads Community Church.
Also with our network of churches, I'm our youth director.
And I've just been fortunate enough to be invited back.
Now, this is my third time, man.
That's, you know, I haven't offended you yet.
So hopefully today, we can, you know, I can continue in my not being offensive.
But I am excited to get to join in on this series.
I've been following this, practicing the way since before it was really being brought forth.
And so I was excited to hear that you guys here at Canvas, we're going to slowly incorporate
some of this into your sermon series and practices in your small groups.
And so very encouraged by your heart here and your willingness to just do what you can to become like Jesus.
That's really our goal.
Our goal in life as Christians is to become like Christ.
It's not to become like me, even though Paul says, follow me as I follow Christ.
Paul wasn't inviting them to become like him.
He says, follow me as I follow Christ, because Paul was following Jesus.
He was inviting them to become like Jesus because he believed that he was becoming like Jesus.
And so that's really important, especially when we bring into a topic like fasting,
which is not a cool, fun thing to preach on.
And it's even less fun to actually do.
Amen.
If you've ever tried to Lent, like we're currently in, is an incredible, is an intentional fasting
period that leading up to Passover, like you're going to have a Seder meal sort of here coming
up soon.
So over the 40 days leading up to Easter resurrection Sunday, whichever you prefer to call it, this
is a beautiful time in the body of Christ where globally the church is doing something together
at one moment for a specific reason.
There is something powerful when the whole body of Christ comes together.
However, we should not view or practice this as a religious, a religious ritual or obligatory
deed.
Help me out.
That if we don't practice this, we're in some way bad Christians or dishonoring God.
Don't think like that.
The battle, I mean, actually, hold on.
There's examples of people fasting in times throughout history when national days of prayer have been
called.
One specifically is the battle of Dunkirk, if you're familiar with it, during World War II,
when Winston Churchill called for a day of fasting and prayer because 300,000 British troops were
stranded on a beach and the German soldiers were in, were in, uh, coming up a pun and cornering
them between the ocean and land.
Oddly enough, though, this is weird that the Germans stopped advancing and gave the British
time to try to figure out what to do.
We can debate on whether or not it was a bad move by the German army or a chance of a foggy
morning, which provided the cover for the boats to arrive through a tough journey over the English
channel to rescue these stranded soldiers.
But the fact remains that after a national day of prayer was called, these soldiers were
rescued.
This sounds like a choose your own adventure book.
You can choose to believe that just by happenstance, a foggy morning happened.
The German soldiers stopped and fishing boats arrived to rescue 300,000 soldiers.
That's a lot of boats.
I don't know if any of you go down to, uh, the Chesapeake to do any type of, you know,
a charter boat fishing, but those boats can only hold so many people.
And those are big boats compared to who knows the size of the boats really that showed up to
rescue all these soldiers.
I'm going to choose to not believe that that was happenstance.
Fasting is one practice though, that I can conveniently forget.
But I'm reminded of the importance of it when it's being, when I'm practicing.
In my early zealousness for Christ, in my walk with him, I fasted weekly.
But I found myself becoming extremely prideful in how I was fasting.
And in my mind, I thought if I fasted once a week, that means I'm going to fast 52 days this year.
Man, I'm doing a good job.
Man was my motive on why I was fasting exposed.
My desire for the denial of my flesh was met because that was the importance of what I was trying to do.
However, my mind derailed what the true goal really was.
And that's to become like Christ.
So I ask you these questions.
Do we have a desired outcome when you're fasting?
Is that for God to be heard more clearly to you?
Or what's God's response to prayer and fasting?
And stories or testimonies like the Dunkirk story that we just heard,
are they God's response to fasting and prayer or just mere coincidence?
What we have before us this morning is a few things.
First, is what we know for sure is that throughout Scripture, fasting and prayer are found together.
It's not always said together, but a lot of the times, especially in the Old Testament,
you see Israel fasting and praying.
And a lot of the times, it's as a community, not just as an individual.
Number two, we can pray without fasting, but you cannot fast without praying.
I don't know if any of you have ever done an extended fast over more than a couple of days,
but you definitely need the Spirit of the Lord to continue,
for you to continue to be connected to Him, because it is very tough.
You feel weak, you feel tired, but guess what?
What does the Spirit of the Lord do?
He really does strengthen you up.
Then you're like, man, I can keep going forward.
I don't need to eat today.
Then today's message, fasting to amplify your prayers,
will be boiled down into a core discipline in following Christ.
That's the hearing God.
But then we're going to throw in something spicy at the end.
Now this is what, now let's get into,
this is the third of the four reasons why we fast.
Let's do a brief recap.
So week one, you reviewed or you discussed in your small groups and here,
hopefully on Sunday, I didn't listen to the whole message,
but I listened to part of it,
is offering ourselves to Jesus was covered.
Week two was fasting for holiness.
Michelle did a great job.
Now this week is fasting to amplify your prayers.
Now before you check out or write questions to Pastor Ryan to try to clarify a few things.
First, prayer can be distilled into two categories.
And I know that you've already discussed that in the first four week series,
but it's really prayer is boiled down or distilled into two things.
That's listening to God and God speaking to you.
Two things.
I know that that's an oversimplification,
but for people like me, I really do need it simple,
even though I like to study complex things.
The point in the complex is to make it simple,
because sometimes our lives are deeply complex,
but yet ever so simple.
Prayer is a bit of an umbrella term
that essentially covers our methods or ways of communing with God,
that is by listening and speaking.
Fasting is deeply powerful,
and it amplifies our prayers both for us hearing and for God speaking.
Let's put it this way.
Here's a quote from Reverend Sam Rogers.
Prayer is not being modified by my fasting.
I am being modified by my fasting.
Fasting is a way to hear God and be heard by God.
Very wise words.
Number one, let's jump into today's sermon.
To hear God.
Let's everybody turn to Acts chapter 13, one through three,
and we're going to read this portion of Scripture
and read a fascinating story of some of the early disciples along the way.
I'm going to be reading from the NASB,
and so you can follow along there,
or you can follow along by reading on the screen.
They say this,
Now there were at Antioch in the church that was their prophets and teachers,
Barnabas and Simeon, who was called Niger,
and Lucius of Cyrene and Manine,
who had been brought up with Herod the Tetrarch and Saul.
While they were ministering to the Lord and fasting,
the Holy Spirit said,
set them apart for me, Barnabas and Saul,
to do the work of the church,
or for do the work which I've called them.
Then, when they had fasted and prayed,
they laid their hands on them,
and they sent them away.
Notice how clear God was
when they were ministering and fasting.
What would we associate that word ministering to?
What were we doing just a few minutes ago
when we were singing that last song?
We weren't singing about ourselves in that song.
You weren't calling yourself a wretched sinner in that song,
and although that might be true for those of us
who might not be following Christ.
But what were we doing in that last song?
We were declaring,
How great are you, Lord?
We were praying and saying words of affirmation to God,
not to ourselves,
not to you,
and most of you are probably great people.
But you're not God.
I'm sorry.
But we were declaring to Him
who He is.
And through that ministering and fasting,
meaning that we're not eating
and declaring who great God is,
even though we bless our food
and I love a good meal, clearly.
But while they were abstaining from eating
and ministering to the Lord,
Holy Spirit spoke very clearly.
Scott McKnight says this
in his Second Testament translation.
He says,
They're performing a religious service to the Lord
and fasting.
Another word for this is worship.
They were worshiping and fasting.
Then they heard the Lord speak clearly.
But I thought today's is why fasting amplifies our prayers.
Why are we pointing this out?
Because worship,
I don't want to say it's a form of prayer,
but it kind of is.
Because you're communing with God.
We are speaking to the Lord.
We are declaring who He is.
Yes, there's times when we fast because,
or we're praying because we have a need
that needs to be met,
whether it's a family member that's hurt
or, you know, dealing with an addiction.
We're praying for the Lord to bring them along
or we have a dire need at the church
that, you know, we need something happens
and we're praying to the Lord for this.
You're communing with God.
So as they were worshiping to the Lord
and fasting, Holy Spirit spoke.
Now I do, the teacher in me needs to find some examples
of fasting and prayer.
So let's turn to Daniel chapter 10,
very familiar portion of Scripture.
Daniel in chapter 10 says this,
In those days, I, Daniel had been mourning for three weeks.
I did not eat any tasty food, nor meat or wine into my mouth,
nor did I use any ointment at all until the entire three weeks were completed.
Daniel fasted for three weeks.
And I know that now in our modern Western church,
we have moved into, I don't know if you guys do this here,
but it's very common that we do a Daniel fast
where you don't eat any tasty food.
So it's okay to eat raw vegetables.
That's fine.
I'm not saying raw vegetables aren't tasty,
but come on, if there's not salt and pepper on it or butter,
come on, dude.
He didn't eat anything for three weeks.
And then at the end of that three weeks,
the Lord answered his prayers.
One more example.
That's going to be in Nehemiah chapter four,
chapter one, verse four through 11.
Now I was going to paraphrase this,
but I'm just going to read some of it.
When that, when I heard these words,
I sat down and wept and mourned for days.
And I was fasting and praying before the God of heaven.
Nehemiah needed to fast and pray before God
because of something in very important
that was happening for him.
He needed attentive ears and eyes
to be able to see and hear what the Lord was doing.
and what the Lord was speaking.
Why did he need to have attentive ears?
Because sometimes maybe our flesh gets in the way, perhaps.
I mean, I know sometimes after I eat a big meal,
I can get a little, little woozy,
eat too much cheese and your head feels weird.
I don't know if that's happened to you,
but dairy can do that to me sometimes.
Why do we see this in Scripture?
But also why is it rare that we see this lived out
in our modern culture?
We don't have time to dissect this fully,
but we should,
but we should choose not to find where to place blame or fault,
but rather allow the Scriptures to speak for themselves
and not us impose our personal
and sometimes even frail theological
or ideological beliefs on the Scriptures
so that we can learn from them
and not tell the Scriptures what we want them to say to us.
Can we do that?
That's hard.
Trust me.
I've been walking down this road
not as long as some of you,
but let the Scriptures speak for themselves
and not me impose my frailed thought on top of it.
You can think of it like this.
In times of prayer and fasting,
we are waiting on God
and this postures us for hearing God,
but let us remember it is not the only way,
but a powerful one.
Now, this part's going to be a little challenging for me
because we want to take a step back
and sort of look at our body
and how our body responds in fasting.
Remember, we're chipping away at false dichotomies
between the physical and spiritual.
We are whole persons,
but what we do with our body affects our soul.
In the last session,
you covered some of the ways that fasting is good
for your physical health,
but also good for your mental health.
Peer review studies on fasting have demonstrated
that fasting increases your blood flow,
that causing you to be more alert and aware
and compared to eating,
which causes blood flow to go to your digestive system,
which is why we're tired and cloudy
in our minds after a large Thanksgiving
or even Christmas meal.
This also increases our neuroplasticity.
That's a big word.
And I almost pronounced it correctly.
The ability for your brain to make new neuro connections.
Wow.
Nick did it.
If any of you really know me, that was tough.
It's also proven to decrease our neurotransmitters
that signal anxiety and depression
and increase those that elevate and calm
and give us a sense of well-being.
That sounds really important.
It's also proven to increase
what doctors call interception,
which is your ability to accurately notice
what's happening inside your body and mind.
Fasting seems very important.
It's even been shown in some studies
to arrest or even reverse the effects of Alzheimer's.
It comes as no surprise that fasting
is not an exclusively Christian practice.
It's practiced widely around different religions, societies,
but the first time it's really mentioned
that we can see is in Scripture
with Moses fasting on Mount Sinai for 40 days.
And what was Moses feeding on?
The very presence of Yahweh for 40 days.
Now, we think Israel's in the desert.
It was probably easy for them to fast
because food was hard to come by.
I doubt it.
The Lord was constantly feeding them
even though they were very...
they grumbled heavily.
And there was a lot of them
and God was constantly feeding them,
whether it's through manna or quail.
Because fasting is a way of honoring
our body and mind to a point of alertness,
focus, and perception.
Now to repeat,
this does not happen overnight.
If you are new to fasting
and especially if your regular diet
is high in sugar or refined in grains,
do not just start fasting.
Be very cautious in how you walk into the waters
because it can hurt your body.
And even as I do minister with a lot of youth
and young adults,
we don't encourage teenagers to do much fasting.
And that's not because I was raised Catholic
and within the Catholic faith for during Lent,
teenagers are not supposed to fast in over 65.
You're supposed to be very cautious in what you fast.
Because young people are still developing
and we don't want to hurt development of their brain.
It's very important.
Now they could skip a meal here and there,
but I know some of you would probably enjoy that
in your wallet and your fridge would.
May not drink a gallon of milk in a day.
But the point is is that fasting helps us
in our body, our mind, and our soul.
If you want to practice this
and make it regularly a part,
I'm not sure how much you've touched on already
the rule of life,
which is really how you develop your rules in life.
And I don't mean rules as in
here's a one, two, three rules you have to do.
Rule is more of a Latin word that means trellis.
Here's a trellis that's built
that allows my vine to grow.
Does that make sense?
So how incorporate fasting into your rule of life,
how you develop, how you are following God,
how are you allowing the vine,
which is the Lord in you to grow,
becoming more like him.
It's important for us to understand
that fasting is not a way
to get a better response to prayer,
but rather true fasting means
that we are fostering a better,
humbler approach to prayer.
Again, it's not a religious right
that you have to do.
It's one that we actually get to do,
which is kind of fascinating to think about.
It's important for us to not only see
but understand how this all puts our body,
our mind in an ideal state or posture
to hear God's voice.
Something to mention really quick though.
Fasting creates space in your lives too.
You don't, I mean, think about it.
How much in a week do you think about food?
Where you're going to get food?
Husbands, ask your wives.
What you're going to eat that week
if you're meal planning,
if you get home at the end of the day
and you haven't thought about what's for dinner
and then you get tired
and then you order food
if you don't live out deep in the country?
You know, how much time are you putting
and effort are we putting into food
in our daily lives?
It's not a bad thing.
It's just let's look at it holistically.
Fasting creates space
to where we don't have to meal plan.
Now again, that's not every week
but think about it.
We put a lot of time and effort into food.
Priscilla Shear says this about her fasting practice.
I am able to gain perspective
on how unbalanced the amount of time,
the energy and effort
that I've put into my body and spirit.
When we choose to sacrifice a need of the body
to place more importance on the need of the spirit,
God himself sits up and takes notice.
This is her personal journey.
The heavens are opened to us
in a way that we may not have otherwise been.
She offers a key insight here.
Not only does fasting put us
in an ideal position to listen
but it puts God in an ideal position for us
for him to speak.
I know that might sound strange for some of us
but let's continue
and I want you to hear me out.
Not only is our mind attentive
but our heart is humble and hungry.
Let us consider what the prophet Joel said
in chapter 2
verse 12 and 13.
I'm almost there.
Now then the people of Nineveh believed in God
and they called a fast
and put on sackcloth
from the greatest to the least of them.
Then the word reached the king of Nineveh.
He arose from his throne,
laid aside his robe from him,
covered himself with sackcloth
and sat in the ashes.
He instituted,
he issued a proclamation
and said in Nineveh
by the decree of the king
and his nobles
do not let man,
beast,
herd,
or flock
taste the thing.
Do not let them eat
or drink water.
He was like
don't even feed
your cattle.
That's crazy
that it wasn't just a fast
for the people
but it was a fast
for all God's creation.
But both man and beast
must be covered
in sackcloth
and let man
call on God
earnestly
that each
may turn
from his wicked way
and from the violence
which is on his hands.
Who knows
God may turn
and relent
and withdraw
his burning anger
so that we
will not perish.
When God
saw their deeds
that they
turned
from their wicked way
then God
relented
concerning
calamity
which he
had declared
what he would
bring upon them.
Immediately
we see
God
recognize
what they were
doing
and
relented.
Very fascinating.
What we see here
and what we
really see
throughout the
Old Testament
are times
when fasting
fasting is vitally
important
to the lives
and the followers
of Yahweh.
This discipline
of fasting
and listening
for God's voice
is a part
of the larger
and spiritual
journey
from making
decisions
and even
discernment.
This helps us
place our reliance
on God
and his spirit
and not on
ourselves.
And this
isn't to mitigate
or take away
wisdom
that we've
learned
throughout life.
Okay?
Wisdom
will tell you
a child
touches a hot
stove
and they won't
touch it again
hopefully.
Wisdom
is okay
with that.
But sometimes
we need to rely
on God's
spirit
for wisdom.
And it
takes an
intentional
thing
of removing
our own
flesh
from being
able
to hear
God.
This also
leads us
into an
even deeper
movement
of our
spiritual
journey
from
control
to
surrender.
How many
in this
room
really like
to be in
charge
of a
situation?
Like leadership
just kind
of rises
up and
you would
actively
seek
to take
control
in a
situation?
Now that's
not what
I'm talking
about here.
what I'm
talking
about is
control
of your
spiritual
journey
of following
Christ.
Of
surrendering
to Him
and what
He says
versus
what we
think
our lives
should be.
I know
that's a
challenging
thing for
some of us
here because
we're like
wait a
minute I've
been taught
these things
I've learned
and that's
not to
say that
you've
been taught
wrong or
taught
poorly
but what
I'm
saying is
are you
surrendered
to Christ
to allow
Him to
be the
one who
leads
you?
That
leader
can be
following
Christ
and that's
fine but
man I'm
flawed dude
come hang
out with me
for a few
hours you'd
know I'm
not this
I'm clearly
most of you
I'm not
perfect.
Emily's
right there
she'll tell
you there's
a few others
in here that
will back
up that
claim.
but are
you surrendered
am I
surrendered
to Christ
you better
believe it
how important
our surrender
is
are you
am I in
control of
my life
or am I
the Lord's
servant
doing it
according to
your word
Lord
fasting is
a discipline
by which
opens our
body and
soul to
God's
spirit to
facilitate
essential
movements deep
within ourselves
it's easy
to say a
prayer that
somebody's leading
you in and
then you can
think man I
just accepted
Christ into my
life that's
beautiful but
then where's the
rest of the
journey taking
you is the
you to be
formed into
his image or
is a journey
taking you that
oh I said
this prayer and
I don't I can
just continue to
be me is
Christ making
his indwelling
in yourself I'm
not judging I'm
just asking and
this is for us
as people that
want to lead
others into
Christ are we
just getting them
to say a
prayer or are
we getting them
to walk into
the deeply
formed life of
following him
and I know
that that's
tough it's
challenging but
we need to
learn more about
denying of
ourself and
allowing Christ
to be at the
front of it
which leads us
in to the
beautiful deeply
formed journey
of following
him I told
you at the
beginning we're
gonna say I'm
gonna say
something spicy
and it might
not be that
spicy but it's
I want to be
heard by God
that sounds
a little
selfish
that sounds
slightly
spiritually
narcissistic
that I want
God to hear
me
but I want
God to hear
me
I want
to be heard
by God
for some of
us these words
can be kind
of a red flag
and I get it
I get it
but let me
remove that
barrier that
may be forming
we are not
fasting to
pressure God
into hearing
us and
ignore others
we need to
be very
careful
let's look at
it like this
fasting is
denying the
most basic
fleshly need
and our
cravings
require us
to have
food
we are
denying
the most
basic
need we
have
which is
food and
water
however
when we're
fasting
we are
quieting
the voice
of our
fleshly
need
you're
quieting
the voice
of your
fleshly
need
and allowing
the spirit
of the
Lord
to fulfill
that need
Lord I
need you
in this
moment
because I
want your
spirit
to be
the
loudest
thing
that I
hear
there's
a song
and I
can't
remember
if it
was
Rick
Pino
or if
it was
Dutch
Sheets
that was
saying it
but he
was like
praying that
Lord I
want your
voice to be
the loudest
thing I
hear
I need
it
and he
learned
in college
this is a
interesting
fun fasting
story that
I don't know
if you're
familiar with
Dutch
Sheets
he's a
fairly
prominent
man of
God
that was
very
influential
for us
in the
beginning
parts of our
walk with
Christ
but he
said this
while he
was at
Bible
college
that he
wanted to
get up
early to
have
devotion
then he
would go
to breakfast
and he
would go
off to
class
but he
was finding
himself
sleeping
in so
he didn't
have
devotion
and then he
would go
to breakfast
and then he
would go
to class
so he
was like
flesh
what are
you doing
I want
to get
up
early
but then
the next
day
he'd
try to
get up
early
he'd
want to
sleep
in
then he'd
go to
breakfast
then he'd
go to
class
and he
was missing
his
devotion
so he
got to
this point
that he
said I'm
done with
this
flesh
if you
don't get
up
before
if I
don't get
up
in order
to have
devotion
before I
go to
breakfast
you can't
have
breakfast
this
morning
and now
that takes
a very
special
thing
to allow
yourself
to do
that
and it's
only the
spirit
of God
because
you're
in control
of yourself
he
and
his
story
was
and the
journey
was
that's
what he
did
he beat
his flesh
up
by fasting
so that
if you
want
breakfast
you got
to get
up 45
minutes
before we're
supposed
to
so that
I can
have
we can
devotion
then we
can
have
breakfast
then we
go to
class
fasting
beat his
flesh
up
because
he
wanted
God's
voice
to be
the
loudest
thing
and not
the
need
of
eating
even
though
remember
I get
it
I love
to eat
I'm
really
good
at
eating
but
fasting
enables
me
to be
able
to hear
God
more
clearly
and this
isn't
me
on some
like
when Ryan
asked me
that actually
when I was
I don't know
if I drew
a short
straw or
what for
this topic
but when I
saw on the
list that
this is the
one that
I had
I immediately
thought like
man
I don't
typically
fast and
pray for
an outcome
and not
that like
the Lord
just blesses
me with
outcomes
but I
don't find
myself
and Emily
and I
both were
dissecting
this
I don't
find
ourselves
like
okay
I need
this
need
to be
met
in my
life
Lord
I'm
fasting
and praying
for that
need
to be
met
I have
not
had
a track
record
of doing
that
but I
was like
Lord
what is
the focus
in here
and he
ever so
quickly
brought me
to remembrance
it's not
about the
desired outcome
it's about
hearing my
voice
so what
if you
don't
fast
and pray
for an
outcome
Lord I
need this
new house
I'm
fasting
and praying
for a
realtor
to come
into my
site
so that I
can get
this new
home
no
it's about
hearing his
voice
ever so
clear
and that
was very
freeing for
me as I
finished
putting the
sermon notes
together
there's a lot
of mystery
in all of
this
Scriptures
tells us
what
and when
we add
fasting
in a higher
correlation
with requests
and God's
release of
his power
there's so
much
mystery
in
Scripture
and a
lot of
it is
around
you know
this topic
is very
mysterious
and different
streams of
the church
have even
different
theories
and
theologies
as to
why
and John
Mark
Comer
who was
responsible
for most
of the
teachings
that
are
the
principles
that are
coming out
in some
of these
teachings
he said
this is
what he
says
he says
my
theory
is
it's
because
God's
relational
and his
ultimate
aim
is to
draw us
into the
inner life
of the
trinity
with prayer
and fasting
takes us
deeper
into this
union
with God
as I've
said
as he said
in the last
lesson
it burns
away
whatever
is creating
relational
distances
between
us and
God
my personal
or as
Scott
McKnight
calls it
his
lived
theology
is
that
there
is
power
in
fasting
because
when
we
because
are
most
basic
of our
when
our
most
basic
need
of our
flesh
is being
denied
and met
by the
power
of God
that's
the
nourishment
that we
need
I know
that that
was a little
confusing
and jumbled
let me
say it
one more
time
because it
was very
confusing
in my
head
there is
power
in fasting
because we
are most
basic
of our
fleshly
need
being met
the most
basic
need
of our
flesh
is fasting
and it
is met
by the
power
of God
fulfilling
our
need
of
nourishment
it is
only
by his
spirit
you may
have another
take
another
diverse
array
of
theologies
and opinions
around the
church
of
Jesus
on why
some
prayers
are answered
and others
are not
but one
thing is
clear
that God
responds
to prayer
and fasting
as we
just read
in Jonah
the Ninevites
believed God
and he
relented
in his
words
this is a
really interesting
thing that we're
going to dissect
into really
quick
because some
of you are
going to
read that
and think
in some
of your
versions
it might
say God
repented
and that's
a really
odd word
why would
God
repent
that doesn't
sound right
but sometimes
in Scripture
the same
word is
used
multiple
ways
especially
in the
Old Testament
and a
beautiful
example
is the
word
Elohim
is anybody
familiar
with this
word
awesome
well not
many of you
raised your
hands
you're
gonna have
to listen
to me
Elohim
is
translated
multiple
ways
singular
God
multiple
gods
and
God
who's
not
Yahweh
sometimes
it's
God
as
sometimes
it's
God
as
Trinity
sometimes
it's
a
false
God
the
same
word
so you'll
read it
especially
in Psalm
it says
Elohim
stood in
the midst
of the
other
Elohim
you look
at that
God
stood
in the
midst
of
the
God
that
doesn't
make
any
sense
but
it's
the
same
word
used
multiple
ways
that's
why
context
and
understanding
language
matters
a lot
the same
thing
goes
for this
word
here
because
it says
that
when
Nineveh
repented
God
but it
should read
when Nineveh
repented
God
relented
that means
he
did not
choose
to bring
upon
them
what
do
was
them
because
they
actually
repented
of their
wickedness
I'm
not
saying
that
God
changed
his
mind
because
we
could
argue
that
in
some
other
Scriptures
but we're
not
talking
about
this
year
God
didn't
change
his
mind
God's
characteristic
of
who
his
character
decided
the
answer
to
what
was
happening
and
his
answer
was
they
repented
so
I'm
going
to
relent
I
am
not
going
to
unleash
on
them
what
is
due
them
because
they
actually
repented
not
just
like
I'm
sorry
Lord
I'm
not
going
to
do
that
again
no
even
the
king
sent
out
a
decree
and
said
everything
must
fast
everything
must
fast
and
pray
man
it
is
amazing
what
happens
when
this
takes
place
Arthur
Willis
says
God's
children
still
on
okay
sorry
I didn't
hear it
for a second
he says
because
man
repents
in respect
to sin
God
repents
in respect
to judgment
and relent
man's
change
of heart
makes it
morally
possible
for God
to behave
towards
is that
me
maybe if I
hold it
out
it's in
my back
pocket
man's
change
of heart
makes it
morally
responsible
for God
to behave
differently
towards him
yet acting
consistently
with his
holy character
and principles
we are
often
mistakenly
assume
that God
is going
to do
what God
is going
to do
with or
without
prayer
but the
pattern
we read
all throughout
Scripture
is when
God's
people pray
and especially
when they
fast
he responds
why does
he respond
I mean I
personally think
that because
fasting is
revealing that
Lord I'm
willing to
give up
this thing
that I
know
I need
because I
need you
more
how important
is that
the Jonah
story is
just one
there's many
other
examples
let's end
on this
all to
say
that when
it comes
to hearing
and being
heard by
God
not only
is fasting
an aid
to prayer
but it
is an
amplifier
and any
of you
play music
you can
play a
guitar
without an
amplifier
and you
don't hear
anything
plug in the
amplifier
and all of a
sudden the
sound goes
out everywhere
but let's
remember this
the end goal
of prayer
is not
ultimately
to get
out of it
what we
want from
God
but to
get God
himself
it's
union
to enter
the inner
life of
the Trinity
with the
Father
the Son
and the
Holy Spirit
their love
over you
and speak
back love
and truth
to you
it's union
with God
my whole
life
my journey
my following
God
is becoming
more and more
about union
with him
and nothing
else
it has
to be
simple
it has
to be
about the
presence
of God
and fasting
enables me
to get
myself
out of the
way
in order
to get
my body
in alignment
a little bit
more
with what
God is
doing
so when
you need
to hear
God
or when
you need
to be
heard by
God
consider
practicing
fasting
let's
pray
Father
in Jesus
name
Lord
we walk
into
this life
very
cautiously
intentionally
and we
walk
into
even
understanding
and then
walking out
of practice
of fasting
Lord
even more
intentionally
because
one
we want
to be
one
with
you
it's
not
our
desire
to just
become
great
amongst
men
but our
desire
Father
I pray
becomes
to be
one
with
you
just
as
Jesus
in the
garden
in
John
as he's
praying
and he
has asked
his
disciples
to fast
and pray
and yet
even though
they fell
asleep
Jesus
still
said
the
words
that
I
be
in
them
that
those
come
after
them
would
hear
these
words
and be
one
with
you
and so
Father
I just
pray
in
Jesus
name
that
you
would
work
out
in
each
one
of
us
what
that
looks
like
and
Father
I
pray
for
your
spirit
right
now
Lord
to
even
work
through
or
to
reveal
each
one
of
us
Lord
Lord
and
let
that
be
the
catalyst
that
reveals
the
depths
of
your
life
inside
each
one
of
us
Father
we
bless
you
in
Jesus
name
Amen
because
I get
to
hand
off
hard
things
like
this
to
good
friends
like
Nick
no
thank
you
very
much
I
think
you
handled
it
well
it's
a
there's
mystery
here
right
there's
mystery
in
this
tension
and as
I've
been
meditating
on it
I
thought
about
that
verse
Holly
read
at
our
time
of
worship
the
father's
prayer
to
Jesus
I
believe
but
help
me
overcome
my
unbelief
I
think
fasting
with
our
whole
selves
say
that
to
God
I
believe
the
same
God
that
raised
Jesus
from
the
dead
can
and
is
working
in
whatever
situations
I'm
dealing
with
struggling
praying
through
but
help
me
overcome
my
unbelief
so
as we
conclude
the
service
I
really
want
to
take
some
dedicated
time
and
prayer
for
some
things
that
I'm
sure
many
of us
in this
room
are
struggling
with
many
of us
have
probably
been
praying
for
days
weeks
months
sometimes
years
for
certain
things
to
happen
and
they
seem
to
be
in
line
with
God's
will
right
we're
praying
something
that
we know
God
desires
healing
he
desires
salvation
he
desires
justice
he
desires
peace
these
are
areas
of
his
character
that
we're
convinced
of
we're
praying
in
accordance
with
it
and
yet
we're
not
seeing
it
happen
do me
a favor
here
I'm
gonna
ask
a couple
questions
and if
if
this
resonates
with
you
raise
your
hand
number
one
raise
your
hand
if
someone
you
care
about
is
struggling
with
a
physical
or
mental
illness
that
you
are
praying
for
God
to
heal
look
around
the
room
pretty
much
all
of
us
raise
your
hand
if
someone
you
love
is
dealing
with
a
broken
relationship
that
you
long
to
see
restored
raise
your
hand
if
someone
you
love
has
walked
away
from
the
Lord
and
you're
praying
that
God
will
bring
them
back
raise
your
hand
if
someone
you
love
has
a
physical
or
financial
need
that
you
are
praying
God
will
miraculously
provide
for
lastly
raise
your
hand
if
you've
been
consistently
praying
for
something
that
seems
like
it's
consistent
with
God's
will
and
yet
the
prayer
has
been
unanswered
so
there's
mystery
here
right
I'm
not
saying
that
fasting
fixes
everything
and
there's
tension
and we
wrestle
with
God
about
why
is
he
not
seeming
to
answer
the
things
that
we
feel
like
he
should
right
there's
this
tension
and
we
find
it
in
the
Lord's
prayer
when
we
pray
God
your
kingdom
come
your
will
be
done
on
earth
as
it
is
in
heaven
I
found
this
quote
from
David
Platt
that
I
think
summarizes
all of
this
really
well
he
says
praying
and
all
of
our
fasting
and
pursuit
of
God
will
culminate
in
the
goal
of
our
salvation
everlasting
uninterrupted
uninhibited
unimaginable
indescribable
all
satisfying
communion
with
God
the
reality
is
God
will
miraculously
show up
and answer
prayers
on
earth
before
he
brings
heaven
to
earth
but
for
those
prayers
that
remain
unanswered
one
day
heaven
will
come
to
earth
and
all
of
our
prayers
that
are
in
line
with
God's
will
we
see
happen
I
love
think
it's
Habakkuk
that
the
glory
of
the
Lord
will
fill
the
earth
as
the
waters
cover
the
sea
we
will
see
our
prayers
answered
meantime
in
the
tension
in
the
mystery
we
wrestle
fast
we
pray
ask
of
like
the
father
I
believe
help
me
overcome
my
unbelief
so
again
fasting
this
is
just
an
invitation
for
you
to
consider
there's
multiple
reasons
why
you
might
consider
fasting
we
talked
about
three
so
far
I
have
a
group
of
individuals
that
I
am
close
with
that
we
just
decided
one
day
a
week
from
now
till
Easter
we
are
going
to
pray
for
the
salvation
of
these
people
that
we
love
not
saying
that
that's
a
golden
ticket
that
I
got
the
award
and
it's
going
to
happen
but
we
we're
praying
and
we're
making
an
invitation
on
Easter
Sunday
but
I'm
still
going
to
trust
him
because
he's
faithful
so
I
just
want
to
take
this
time
at
the
end
of
service
to
just
pray
for
those
things
that
we
raised
our
hands
about
pray
for
those
areas
people
so
as
I'm
praying
over
these
areas
just
bring
to
mind
the
person
situation
that
you're
praying
for
and
join
me
in
praying
that
God
might
show
thankful
that
you
invite
us
to
pray
we
are
so
thankful
of
testimonies
people
in
this
room
where
you
have
showed
up
and
done
miraculous
things
testimonies
in
the
Scriptures
of
you
showing
up
and
doing
miraculous
things
and
we
believe
that
the
same
God
that
raised
Jesus
from
the
dead
has
power
over
death
sin
and
the
grave
in
this
life
and
in
the
life
to
come
so
God
we
pray
that
your
kingdom
will
come
on
earth
as
it
is
in
heaven
that
your
kingdom
will
invade
the
situations
of
our
life
where
your
kingdom
is
not
yet
clear
it's
not
visible
God
we
pray
for
those
who
have
mental
and
physical
illnesses
things
that
have
been
going
on
for
weeks
months
years
decades
we
pray
God
that
you
would
show
up
you
choose
to
show
up
miraculously
supernaturally
God
that
you
would
show
off
your
goodness
and
your
faithfulness
not
because
you
have
to
not
because
we
deserve
it
but
because
you're
good
God
may
your
kingdom
come
and
your
will
be
done
in
the
physical
and
mental
illnesses
of
those
we
love
God
for
the
broken
relationships
for
the
marriages
that
have
been
ripped
apart
the
families
that
have
been
ripped
apart
the
prodigals
who
have
walked
away
God
we
desire
to
see
your
kingdom
come
and
your
will
to
be
done
in
the
relationships
that
we
care
about
God
may
you
begin
to
soften
hearts
humble
who
are
holding
grudges
God
may
you
begin
to
show
up
and
supernaturally
miraculously
are
going to
restore
relationships
so that
your
kingdom
may
come
and
your
will
may
be
done
through
these
relationships
that have
been
broken
God
for those
of us
that have
loved
ones
that
have
not
accepted
your
good
news
your
gospel
the way
of
living
that
leads
to
abundant
and
eternal
life
God
we
know
the
Scriptures
say
that
you
desire
that
everyone
should
come
to
know
you
we
desire
that
with
you
we
pray
that
for
those
that
we
love
for
our
family
members
and
our
friends
and
our
co-workers
and
our
neighbors
work
through
our
church
may
we
see
people
come
to
know
you
people
that
we
thought
are
too
far
gone
people
that
we
thought
there's
no
chance
this
person
is
going
to
come
know
doing
Damascus
road
moments
all
around
our
lives
with
people
we
love
may
you
show
you're
rejecting
persecuting
follow
me
and
you
will
find
life
God
may
your
kingdom
come
and
your
will
be
done
in
the
lives
of
those
we
love
that
don't
know
you
God
for
physical
and
financial
provision
this
is
one
we
don't
like
to
pray
in
church
because
it's
been
misused
but
God
you
clothe
the
birds
and
the
lilies
of
the
field
you
care
about
our
physical
and
financial
needs
God
may
you
show
up
through
the
lives
of
believers
or
just
supernaturally
miraculously
provide
for those
who are
hurting
God
may
your
kingdom
come
and
your
will
be
done
in
situations
where
people
are
in
need
Father
lastly
I'm
sure
there
are
other
situations
and
circumstances
that
people
have
been
praying
for
a
long
time
God
they're
confused
maybe
angry
or upset
with
you
God
we
humble
ourselves
before
you
and
we
acknowledge
that
your
thoughts
are not
our
thoughts
that
your
ways
are
not
our
ways
God
we
open
ourselves
to
be
changed
by
you
and
we
continue
to hold
out
hope
that
you
will
show
up
and
that
you
will
bring
your
kingdom
on
earth
as
it
is
in
heaven
God
we
hold
out
hope
until
that
day
comes
but
one
day
Christ
will
return
he'll
wipe
away
every tear
from
our
eyes
there
will
be
no
more
mourning
no
more
pain
no
more
confusions
or
questions
about
unanswered
prayers
here
I hear
Christians
all the
time
say
when
I
come
before
God
I'm
going
to
ask
him
this
no
you're
not
our
questions
will
be
answered
we
trust
you
God
we
believe
help
us
overcome
our
unbelief
Jesus
name
I
pray
amen
all
right
church
you're
dismissed
go
in
peace
to